friends
this is really a great
privilege for us
that some of the great scholars of
tantra and kashmir savism
is an extraordinary scholar
he was initiated by
lakshmanaju
he belongs to that tradition
the another scholar professor kamles jha
he belongs to the
parampara
of kashmir savijam he is one of the rare
scholar
who
come from parampara
who and who are expert of cosmis vision
so we have today a rare combination
of the two traditional tradition
[Music]
initiated by
lakshmanaju as well as
bhai rameshwar jha
and both these were in close contact in
fact
uh rameshwarajha used to
call lachmanju as his diksha guru
but
so far as the scholarship is concerned
lakshmi was very much
influenced and impressed by
the scholarships of scholarship of
aramis
so
we have today these two scholars
mark is
literally
one of the greatest scholars
of
and as i
just told you
that
he
is a disciple of last year
he is a scholar as well as
a spiritualist
a musician
recently he has
completed his lifelong project of
translating tantra look with jayarat
tika
and that is that work is
in more than 10 volumes
it was his lifelong project
for which he spent
at least
40 years
so you can imagine his scholarship
we are
really lucky and in fact it is the
blessing of lord is not that he is with
us in fact four months back i
made contact
to him
i invited him
and he told me that he is leaving
india and would come in september and
october
just
few days back i
just made him where are you mark
and he told me that i am in banaras
so we got his lecture
and we are really
feel blessed that he is with us
same could be said by said
about
professor kum les jha
when i told
mark that professor would preside over
the
lecture
he told me that we are playing with each
other for last 20 years or more than 20
years
so
and the convener today is professor
kejah
he himself
all our students know
that a scholar of tantra and kashmir
vision presently is engaging
the classes of
cosmic servicem
in pg classes
so
i think
our lecture today would be very much
interesting to you
i welcome both these scholars i also
welcome
professor paneer salvamji
who
is always with us in all our seminars
professor
ganesh prasadas professor krishna yaji
professor d.a gangadhar and so many
other scholars
who are
present
online
besides the
audience which is here
offline i welcome all these scholars
students and colleagues
thank you thank you
[Applause]
thank you anji
it was so nice to hear you welcome all
but i must say
that it is all because of your
initiative that this thing is happening
and we are all grateful to you as well
now
we have to come to the main part of the
program and i invite
dr mark degskowski to present his
special lecture
part one
why part one because he will be
presenting basically two lectures in
between we will have a deep deck so i
request him to present the first part of
his lecture
oh
you
my
[Music]
foreign
this is the first manga
i wanted to begin
these are the first three verses
from tantra loka
after the initial verse
in which amir gupta praises
his birth
and prays for inspiration
for us
that we may also be inspired
and that he's born from this union of
an enlightened father enlightened mother
and that is his hallmark for all his
trigger works
then he prays to the three goddesses
this i think is very appropriate
nowadays
we have been studying kashmiri shaivism
since chatterjee
1901.
he published a book called kashmiri
chemism in which he described the 36
chapters
as they are
described in the cash military and the
text
we have largely
ignored
the actual
um
original tantric call
we have been concentrating more
on the exegetical works both scriptural
exegetical works
shiva sutras
commentary on shiva sutras panda karika
um the soman under shivadrishti and the
great uppala devas
is with all the commentaries
and tantra loka
um
i will now explain this in a
minute um the three
avraham gupta
was concerned with tricker shavers
and for this he had to refer back to the
tantras
which the people before him did not do
directly i'll explain this as i go along
so he begins with the prayer to the
three goddesses
as if he were beginning a tantra
as if he were beginning a
trick attempt
is actually puja
this is a padatti
i will just
talk about all this
so he praises the three goddesses
and i'll just read that
and i want to quickly move on
to
there's a lot to to say in a short time
so i i bow to the goddess para
and uh who is the creative intuition of
consciousness chit pratibha
united with him
she has
made her place on top of the
lotus of the tikka trident
the prongs of which
are the aspects of perception
namely
subject object and means of knowledge
we are at ratings
of a completely different character from
we are just opposite
because we
our reality consists of the totality of
everything
in all its forms
imagined non-imagined
a physical form
the whole gamut of all possible existing
things in all formats
illusory non-illusory and so on
with that
now all that is contained within the
parameters
of the what is called trikuta in memsa
this terminology pramatri pramana
pramaya
is formulated in indian philosophy first
of all by kumari bhatta
and he calls this recorder
subject object means of knowledge is
very ancient but the terms
and terms are very important
so she sits on the trident because the
the worship of the goddesses is sitting
on the points of a trident
and the the
the prongs of the trident are subject
object means of knowledge what this
means is
is that the energy of consciousness
the power of consciousness
is cognitive consciousness
sankhya
siddhanta
everybody
considers the cognition takes place
through the senses the mind the body the
cognitive operators
so some are dualists
and they consider that that cognitive
apparatus is separate from consciousness
we believe
that the perception is takes place by
consciousness itself
and that the perception the senses the
mind
the body etc
are instruments through which that
perception takes place that are emanated
from consciousness
in the course of perceiving
whatever is perceived through the sense
is the mind
okay
so it is consciousness itself that
perceives
and consciousness itself that acts
through the organs of action of the body
through the movement of the stars of the
planets
through the whole activity of the uter
universe
from going right the way down to pulsing
of strings
of string theory if you believe in that
right the way up to the whole expansion
of the universe from the big bang
speaking in modern term cosmology okay
so
this pramantri this is
para is present in perceva
para is present in the perception of the
placebo
and para is present in the object of
that perception
this condition is called pervasion
so when in the upanishads it says
um who can know the noah
he is the ear of the hearing he is the
eye of the seeing the nose of the
spelling etc and then who can know them
we say it's not only that we pay
attention
to the brahman
the ultimate reality
which here is
para
the goddess of consciousness some with
devi
in the perceiver
but also in perception
and also in the object of perception
so we may
pay attention
to the presence of deity
which is consciousness
within ourselves as perceivers
within the activity of the senses the
mind
or any other means of knowledge
or within the object of that perception
so these are the three prongs of shiva's
trident okay
so para sits on those three prongs in
union with byron part of his
consciousness she is the power of
consciousness
i bow to the goddess
who resides in the body of bhairava's
dancing for
bhairava's dancing form is this universe
and she is present in that body
and plays within it like a lightning
flash in the sky covered with dense
storm clouds
in this condition of maya
there are moments
flashes
in which we perceive
suddenly in the darkness is illumined
just for a moment
so this is the situation at the level of
maya
there's a darkness
that is to say that prevents us from
perceiving oneness
oneness means lord shiva
and his energy his power
of cognitive consciousness
and
from time to time there are flashes
where
you just get a glimpse
so this is apara
and her film is like kali she's dark
and para para who's red in color
like the three grunas white red and
black
ah this is the goddess
who is radiant
prone of knowledge
the three prongs the world knowledge in
action will is pre-cognitive
consciousness nirvikalpa
it's called the seed state
when you begin to have a perception
the initial moment of perception
begins with the state of thought-free
nerve calper consciousness this is a
condition of potency
potential
that then goes on to develop into a
cognition
key called just ghana
so that state is one of a kind of will
or intention
when i will or intend something that has
not yet taken place
it is simply a tendency towards
something
that i have chosen
that i will that i desire so that is a
difficult path
that's the first problem and that is the
experience of subjectivity
that is the experience of subjectivity
then
comes the experience of cognition
i wish to see the direction there's a
desire to see and that develops into
drishti
perception
and that perception
takes place
he says here
there is the prong of knowledge that has
up to
that has burnt up the triple feta
with its blazing rays of light
of shiver consciousness
when
one is
immersed
sorry
the mic
he's turned up
[Music]
i might come kandiji
okay now cognition
the act of perception
um when it is perceived and experienced
has taken place through consciousness
not just by the sense of the mind
then that act of perception
removes objectivity
and emerges merges that objectivity
so all that is limiting consciousness
which is objective space time and fall
is therefore is dissolved away into the
cognitive act
which is then made
now i wanted to explain this
chapters and teachings
the worship of the trident
the work of the trident
isn't it
this
geez
and throughout estan triloca
as also as paratrinchika vivarna and his
manly video vertica his exposition of
trikachevism is one of the procedures
and the the doctrines that are found at
the scriptural level or that have been
told to him orally by his teacher
shambhunata
and his own exegesis
and it's this that i want to talk about
today
because that is the construction of the
country
and the exegetical methods how little
be put together
right so for that
i will just
now these verses
are drawn from
the commentary on the ngati shastra
by bina gupta
[Music]
having tirelessly climbed
now we observe the genius of the man
when you read abhinav gupta
like the great
other greats
one is continuously pervaded by a sense
of astonishment wonder
by the genius of the man
and his perception
of
here is his perception of what he is
doing
he is telling us he's rather unusual in
this respect
in indian thought
because he not only tells us
um what he thinks
or what he's explaining
from the tantras
but he also every so often
opens a window
into himself
what is taking place within him
and this is important because
this
this means salvific knowledge
what is that knowing which all of this
is not tadaksharam that is the
imperishable that's how mandook
upanishad begins so we're talking about
this guyana
when you have this ganum then you are
liberated
so
um
so having tirelessly climbed
higher and higher
he's talking about himself
you see guru taj
many things in this context it means
like a kasoti
if you
what you are believe
is in accord
with this
then this is correct
and there are three of such pattias and
they are also the source
of gyanam
one is guru
one is scripture
and one is fatah
so in the course of my work of tantra
loca
i have been and analyzing
what comes from his guru
which is considerable
he
refers to his teacher as teaching not
less than 40 things to him
he quotes him as much as he could to
tantra the most
and he teaches him very key concepts
and hermeneutical concepts also
exegetical concepts
and
he also and then of course the shastra
prior to abhinav gupta
shiva sutra was revealed to vasudeva
gupta on a rock
it was not from
the shivagama
it was shivagama
but not in the body of what we call the
pancho-slotas
the five currents of tantra that come
from five faces of shiva avarma dakshina
and
right and left and urdu
these five currents of scripture
no
then
from shiva dristi shivadrishti
is the product has been transmitted from
srikanta
srikanta is lord shiva
he's on kailash
when lord shiva's on kailash is called
tricanter
he says the rishis knew this knowledge
of parama dwaya
but it was being lost so he told durwasa
durvasa then told the whole series of 14
were in the lineage till it reached
triumvika
triamica his descendants two three
generations they came to kashmir and
somananda is from that line
huh okay
so this is an oral tradition
no shaiva
that means the ones from the five
currents of scripture
right
it's
it has
the um authority of scripture
but it is not within those currents of
scripture and that's really something
because by that point
who was a disciple of salman
says at the end of the
year everything i've written here is
from somalia but actually he added very
many things
he considered himself to be an exegete
a commentator
bhagavan gupta considers himself to be a
commentator
now he was also not commenting on
chairman he was commenting on the oral
tradition and it come down to
uh
to some anatomy
now at the end of the shiva drishti
somananda gives an account
of this transmission
and it ends with treyanbaka
triambica then it went to down to sauman
under through his relatives who came to
the kashmir valley
abhinav gupta reproduces that those
verses
with some variants
and he adds another person ardha
treyanbika matika
which was founded by the daughter of
treyarch
and that is tricker shaivism
now the importance of doing that is
because
abhinava gupta in this way connects
the tricker shaivism of the scripture of
the sastras
with the shaivism of treyanbika
that has come down from
okay
right
now what we're dealing with here
therefore
are
in his tantra loka
let me finish this
what we're dealing with
in 40 years i'm very slow you know in my
mind
and maybe what i'm saying now people
will um
am i to speak for a certain period of
time
i'll take at least an hour
because i have the important things to
say
yes i will please don't stop me
i won't be born
no
i'll be very interesting
yes thank
that's why i worked for 50 years not to
be boring
okay thank you
don't mind that
so he's saying here having tyler's
declined higher and higher
the intellect behold the true nature of
things
he's talking about himself
this is the fruit of the series of runs
of discernments
conceived by those who came before now
he's relating
the uniqueness of his insight
with tradition
how is it that i'm abhinav gupta i'm
producing so many new brilliant concepts
one or two will discuss as examples
he's saying no no
there i had there are precedents
how strange me things
how the first descent into the
accomplishment of what is to be known
was without support
means spontaneously it happened to him
by the grace of the goddess this was
swatha siddha
he was swayam siddiqah
which was considered to him the highest
kind of
um
experience or realization that it should
take place
i'm commenting on the word
now but once found the right path it is
no wonder to discover
to discover that bridges and foundations
of cities were already there okay
therefore
the views of the wise have not been
refuted here
rather they have been refined
it is on the basis of the designs that
have been firmly established earlier
that their views are well disposed to
fruit of their original root foundation
this is very important because abhinav
gupta is saying many new things
but he's telling us here that they're
rooted in tradition this in india is
very important
and this is very important because he
says something which would be very
shocking for all of you here
and a complete heresy from a hindu point
of view
don't tell modi
it is possible
for some
in special individuals
with intense shaktipat
grace to receive initiation directly
from deity
they don't need a guru
and this swayam some siddiqah guru
is the most excellent of all
the other gurus
who have reached the same as he has
attained but with the help of others
they're like fireflies before the sun
right
now this is a recurring theme in israel
so this is swata
now
when you are in this condition
of understanding
this is called pratibha
so the pratibha that arises
because she unites you to bhairava which
is your own nature
and what patiba chitratiba means the
inside the genius that come from
consciousness directly
not through the machinations of the
intellect anything like that
kanakanda cardia all that stuff all this
brainy stuff now it comes to direct
insight
right
okay
now
why i'm telling you this is because i'm
going to try
and explain
how he's constructed the tantra loca
on the basis of these three pratyas
and this is very important to understand
because kashmiri shaivism is not the
spunder school the coolest school the
pratya bigger school the tricker school
and they're all going together some kind
of salad
no
all of this is working very coherently
in a way which i'm going to explain that
abhinava gupta put together very nicely
extremely nicely to make it all trigger
he made it all quicker
and he made it trigger
in a scriptural sense
that was very important and uh
now
and he allowed himself
to do so with great imagination but
never losing sight of what is
uh uh scripture and what is the oral
tradition
always with their authority he doesn't
make mistakes
he's astonishing in that way he does not
but he does here and there make
adjustments
now that's fine
so he says who can estimate with
certainty
and he says this is the paratrinchika
remember this man is in his 30s when he
writes tantra locker
he's in his thirties
paratrinchikai was even younger mahali
vijayawatika was even younger when he
did the
guitar
which is not a flicker
he was probably
in his early twenties
or even lately
okay
so he is really
um so i am some siddha
he's something quite astonishing
who can estimate this with certainty
that only so much is present
within the venerable shambhava reality
and his teachings
you're saying
i've extended this incredibly
so who can say with certainty that i've
gone too far
or that i'm not even said enough
and moreover words are without
constraints
you can say what you like
but
then
that which shines within the reality
that is all things
akhil atmony
has manifested to me
to this degree
to the degree in which i have expounded
it in the paratrooper
and i tell you it's a very difficult
book
you got three four years at least it
will take you to read it the first time
and the rest of your life to keep
reading it
so therefore the wise should not be
averse to it they're fighting against
him he's a young man you know who does
he think he
you
right
now we have
to examine
um
i have
in my
if you look at passages examine passages
you find that they are
first of all okay
in order to
make his exegesis complete
he asked for us to do one thing
which he does in the video article
which was written before the paratree in
chicago and the paratrynchika
was written before the tantra
the malini vijay vertica
contains more than 200 verses that are
reproduced in the tantra
but they're in a rather
you cannot understand them without
reading the tantra look
at first i thought
that he wrote the tantra locker and then
he wrote the money vijay vertica because
you could look at the tantra locker and
see what he's talking about
but as it is that's not possible because
he mentions the malibu javartica at the
end of istantraloka as saying
that i am talking about the hierarchy of
scripture
how they are coherent
and how they are all triggered
in the morning
says
that
we find the present time
by piercing through
what is past and what is present and
seeking the immediacy of the present
this method as i have already described
in a previous world and that is
something that is taught it in the video
what is called carla grasa
the consuming of time into the eternity
of consciousness so we know that
manufacturing was before
now all this is important
because
there was one one called the sri purva
panchika
which was also a commentary on the mali
mediocre
is a commentary on the first shlokka
of the mali
and he makes it into 1200 verses
he is moving towards
making a
commentary
which will be his tantra
now what does he do in the manly video
vertica
that opens the way for that
he establishes first of all
what he says here
this seems a very simple statement
but the justification of it
the teachings of the pervasive lord
is divided into groups of ten eighteen
and eight times eight tantras this is a
standard way of referring to the tantra
the canon tantric canon
the essence of which is a tricky
scripture
and the word for essence is sarah
and the essence of that
is the malini mata means
okay
now here he's saying
that trika is the essence of all
scripture here's a simple thing
in the malay video vertica
he explains
that the
the faces of sarah shiva
are progressively uttering
scripture
and progressively higher and higher
levels
when you get to the upper face he utters
the sedan
and beyond the upper face
here also he says
above the upper
then
you the
visage takes place
emission and from this visage takes
place the right and the left the
opposites and from the fusion and
development of these opposites
comes tricker
so he establishes the triggers the
highest
okay that's the beginning
his understanding of the highest we're
not advantages
for us oneness means samasthyam
the whole aggregate
poor
means completeness
from which nothing is excluded
if i say neti neti i'm excluding
duality i'm excluding maya i'm i'm
excluding multiplicity no
so that is forming a kind of duality
between truth and falsity
between what is to be excluded and what
is not excluded right
so purnatha does not exclude anything
it's
now this ontological concept
is applied also to so totiology and the
whole cannon
all the tantras together constitute
trekker
all the tantras constitute tricker in
two ways
one way is taught to him by shambhu nata
it's called shastras and melanin means
the assembly or or the coming together
of the scriptures and that's chapter 35
of tantra loka
in which he says
that the essence of scripture is
prasiddhi
prasiddhi means
many things that we take for a priori
for granted
when i sit to have food
i don't reason
will this food nourish me
when the sun goes down in the evening i
don't worry whether it's going to rise
the next day
no
so much of our daily life
java hara the basic business of life is
based on presidi
i don't go on
questioning every single thing that i do
ah because
we could
nothing is certain and we've had all
kinds of people in the indian tradition
buddhists and nayakas and uh posh anchor
and blatants who've indicated to us that
nothing is certain and their conclusion
for that has been that therefore like
permanentes permanentes
because nothing is sure and nothing is
certain and fixed everything is
transitory everything is changing
nothing has have a
logical certainty that means all of this
is an illusion
here what this presidi presidi avoids
that
is a kind of a priori certainty
now
when you know this is a vocal
okay
now how do i know this is a bottle or
through direct perception is direct
perception valid is it invalid how far
can it see what can it not see if i look
at it this way round is it still a
bottle if i'm seeing it in the distance
do i still see a buckle
etc etc etc etc etc
right
now presidi
simply
accept us okay
so the knowledge that this is a bottle
requires the niche
itself requires presidi
otherwise i'm an ayaka and i say
that i i ascertained this as a book
through the pramanas
but to know that i know
i need another ulterior act of
verification
now to know that i know that i know
there's another actor
and and so on and so on and then the
naiker says it doesn't matter if you
have an infinite regret
because at a certain point it stops
when you're satisfied that it's okay i
mean
this is a bottle
for practical purposes
so even they in some roundabout manner
have to accept the city
okay
now the scripture is made of prasiti
and what is the essence of that prasadi
well yes
trika
if the scripture is correct
what does the scripture say that's
correct
that i am shiva
okay
now that certainty that i am shiva
that becomes entrenched
it's all it's there right at the back of
everything that's going on because
cognitive the whole way perception
epistemology is understood by the school
it requires a fundamental consciousness
which is a cognitive and which
ascertains and validates
and that cannot be temporal that cannot
be spatial that cannot have form etc etc
and you go on and on until you realize
that it has all the properties of what
we call infinite consciousness
right
now for that to work
that is tricker
okay
now in the money vijay vertical we go
back to there
why i started with this was because this
was taught by shambhunata
this is very important because abhinav
gupta more than half of what he teaches
in tantra locker he says he got from
shambhala
more than from any one scripture except
the balini
so in the in the valley of artica what
he does
is he says
there is only one scripture
and that is the only way in which you
can have coherence and non-contradiction
because one of the big problems with
this pramana
the the
pramana
is coherence and non-contradiction one
part of the scripture says one thing
another part says another how are we
going to manage then we decide well
these are not scripture well this is
secondary scripture these are primary
these are secondary there's all kinds of
ways that you can work around that
there are different kinds of statements
that are being made within scripture
some are to do with what one should do
and what we should not do and others are
making ontological statements
okay so we should sort that out and then
we'll find that there are no
contradictions in the ontological
statements
and so on i won't go into that this is a
huge subject you can write many phds
still left to right or not okay
now the navigator says
that the coherence of all scripture is
fine if you accept that all of them are
valid
going from julius cidanta
vegetables and buddhists you have
problems you have to also distinguish
between levels
because our concept of oneness
is that it's everything
all things but ordered in hierarchies
is not everything like chaos
we just say that the one is sebastian
it's everything
then the one would be
a mess
chaos it would be like a heap of garbage
no
but it is the one which is self-ordering
within itself according to principles
of
a hierarchy
of greater and lesser
interaction causality and so on it is a
dynamic oneness of
things all things together that are
interacting as an organic whole
like the body who are very similar to
ramanuja that way
but this is not a vishishtab writer
but it's something like that just to
understand now applying that notion to
scripture
there are thousands of shaivagama they
go from julius cidanta
two extreme left-hand cowlers who
have all these
uh antinomial transgressive and so on
severality which i don't want to go into
i was told that you are young people
so
uh i should say that abhinav gupta
considers that to be the highest form of
ticket checkers by the way
that's not encouraging you to do
anything
they're just telling you that he
considers the most elevated people
the saints the mahatmas
that are qualified for such practice
because they don't worry about cost
they don't worry about pure and impure
their non-duality is that non-duality
of oneness because everything has its
place
in the whole
and in some scriptures
that practice is ordained in other
scriptures it is not we accept all
scriptures within their own place
according to the different kinds of
people that there are
according to their level of realization
according to the sanskaras that they
have received
okay and all of that one scripture of
which all scriptures are apart is yes
you get it
now i can finally get to the point
the essence of trika
which is supreme in this sense not only
because it's at the top but because it
is really everything
is
one tantra
which is called the valley vigil
update
that illusion of course is everything
else that's in all the scriptures
right
so now the stage is set
abhinava gupta
can have full use
of all the shaiva
because trigger shaivism
key is of course distinguishing
that there are lower and higher
there are lower and higher vegetables
are right off the scale
and please no uproar
if i say that's true of vayner also
generally there's an uproar when i say
that
don't get upset
that daddy says that's true available
not uh better is better anyway
good to that buddhist buddhist the worst
invader you'll be glad to know
but it's a common idea if you go to
nepal and you ask the people there what
tantrica
they're brahmins
they'll tell you the tantra is superior
to veda
with a sort of cheeky smile on their
face
okay
so this is a big discussion and not
no time for them
the point is is that
all of each scripture
has its place within the hierarchy
so that he can refer
he's commenting on what is his tantra
locker
next thing he says
after he said that
like how far is it before
so there are many padhati's
the word here for padata usually means a
ritual manual liturgical
in use in diverse currents of scripture
but there is not even one to be seen for
the procedures of allah trigger
so abhinav gupta is going to write the
padatti
and what he is saying in this padhati
which
i'll talk about padathi for a moment
what he's going to say in this padathi
is either directly to be found in the
manly
or else implicitly there
okay
so abhinav gupta here is concerned with
padatti normally now
we have a problem with padathi
the earliest padatti that we have was by
a man called brahma shiva
and that's in a single manuscript in the
park
that's dated about 10 20
current era
but very soon after that
we have soma shambu
uh
the
kriya
kandakramavali
and then after that next generation two
agora shivacari clear
uh the
the
clear
kramavali i forgot now
that is used for all the shaver temples
in south india except
chidambaram and he was 12th century
agora
so within a hundred two hundred years
but that is grew in great number
until it become a way that nowadays
tantras are not being studied much
pandatis are being used simply to do
ritual
kashmiri shaivism the kashmiri shaivites
because of their nature
they rather set aside the
ritual
we don't even know how many people even
did the ritual
that abhinav gupta describes in tantra
loca
um following
the malibu
okay
the whole of tantra locker
is concerned with this ritual
he has
um
and his whole exergetic method
because you see the idea is
everything is immersed in conscious
like a reflection within a mirror
the reflection in the mirror
is not illusory
it's the face i see
in the morning in the mirror is my own
it's not somebody else's
okay
that it is in the mirror is not false
it's not incorrect
but it is
we look for an original image
outside the mirror of consciousness
we can't find it because the image in
the mirror is produced by the energies
within the bureau of consciousness
is produced by the mirror itself
okay
now the purpose of yoga
the purpose of knowledge is to know that
when you know that
if you recognize that then you recognize
that you are the mirror
and this mirror is not just that
individual mirror that is reflecting
what you are perceiving who are
perceiving now
consciousness has no time and space it's
the universal mirror which is shiver
consciousness
so that that recognition brings about
immediate realization of one's own
identity with shiva
now that immediate realization
that comes in a flash
with devastating intensity which is
transformative which is like a kind of
aveisha
possession
which completely changes the person
it isn't just an understanding but it's
a transformation
right
is the ground and foundation of all
possible practice
okay
so abhinav gupta
throughout this time sri lanka
is showing how
the procedures
that are taught in the tantras means
first of all manny vegeta
and then all the other tantras that are
relevant
are all
rituals taking place within
consciousness
and that one with
shiva who is the one doing puja
and he's the object of that puja
and puja itself
he calls vimalsya
now in order to do this he uses certain
exegetical tools
the exegetical tools
are the concepts the philosophical
concepts
that had been worked out
by the people before him
he has a whole
arsenal
of exegetical
tools
so
puja becomes vimarsha
to marsha in the prague
we are told
that shiva is prakash of the martian
maya
the one reality
prakasha means the appearing of things
disappearing
is consciousness one aspect of
consciousness is make things appear
if i'm in coma and nothing appears okay
so that's the kind of fundamental
consciousness which you might call
ground consciousness
in which things are appear and because
of its existence too
like the mirror
then consciousness has this other aspect
which is awareness
in which it knows
what is appearing within it
things appearing
but if they're not known what they
appear what is appearing
then that light would be
incentive
zero
mountains rivers
planets our whole universe
it manifests
but if it's not known
to manifest then it is insentient
right
so that
quality of consciousness
by which things are known that appear
within it it's called the motion
and that dementia consists
of infinite number of energies
because that demarche is the freedom of
consciousness
to appear
in countless numerous ways
through acts of perception
vimarsha is an act of perception
it is the goddess of consciousness
called victory
now in each act of perception
is made up of
seeing tables chairs
emotions
perceivers a whole range of things and
those range of things that are being
perceived
are being perceived by different powers
of vimentia
the power of the matcha to perceive an
object
the power of the martial to taste the
water in this bottle
the power of
to reflect
what this is what this is not
the power of himacha to see that i am me
for you
the power of the marsha to see two
things together and how they're related
etc etc
the capacity to relate things the
capacity to individually perceive what
individual things are
their capacity to appear in countless
forms each of which has its own
functional efficacy
this water has the power to quench
thirst
that is for martials
and the swatantry of consciousness to
appear as the third squanting shakti
this bottle has a capacity to hold
liquids
so that appearing of the bottle with
that shakti
okay so that any single entity is an
aggregate of different
capacities to do this or that
means
functional capacity
right
so that all those functional capacities
are all called shaktis
and all of those shaktis form part of
the one shakti which is the freedom of
consciousness to manifest within the
mirror of its own infinite expanse
everything and to know it
right
now
abhinav gupta can this concept is not in
the tantras
this concept
is not in the tantras in 1990 i
published a paper
okay sorry i one last thing you have to
say when these two things go together
the experiences i am
when
consciousness is
fully aware
then that awareness of itself
and all things is i am
right
it is not the ego of the body
that says i see i hear i touch i smell
i'm marxie i'm mark touch i'm not smelly
it is the eye of lord shiva i am shiva
okay because
that reality is god
not
absolute
it is an absolute god
there's no distinction between ishmael
and brahman here
okay i know we can start or fight
without victims
again because of shakti
remember
that in the time of shankaracharya
who wrote the commentaries on you
there was no concept of shakti
you say wow
i don't believe you montiskowski would
not
read the gita
do you see shakti anywhere there
finding one place in the bhagavad-gita
in upanishads
prior to shwetashwatara
find me one place where the word shakti
appears in a technical sense
not just in the normal everyday round of
the word capacity
not that there isn't an idea of force or
of power
foreign
um
[Music]
okay
now understand how fundamental this is
understand how fundamental this is
when there was the discovery of shakti
and ut
says his philosophy is about the
discovery of
although that took place before
what a huge change
what an immense amount of leeway
it gave
to philosophical thought
so when that shakti
is referred to we call that shaktivimar
it's very i don't think i come again
people stand up and go away
oh he left his back you'll be back
yeah
i usually talk online you know so when
they leave i don't know
i'm telling you things that no one has
published this
what i'm telling you now
has not been published by anybody
and see
what fantastically
important significant point
this is
when shakti is so pervasive in in our
hinduism nowadays
but prior to the 5th century a.d
it did not exist
there was a sense of force of power
in the veda
we are told that the implements have all
jazz
that plays the sacrificial area
has power the uh
sacrifice that has power the word shakti
does not appear
and the concept the extensive concept
behind that does not
even in the devi mahatma
now this is the most mind-blowing
observation of all
turgaji is nowhere called shakti
sink in this
what that means
i one play somebody found it but it's
about many many epiphanes
nowadays this is the characteristic of
durgaji
now
you cannot have
a non-dualism
that is based on anything else except
the idea
the duality is a false
without the concept of shakti
because you can have a one which is
producing the many
and remaining one
because it is all of the many
like platinums
every single thing that the one produces
is one
because of its own inherent capacity to
do that abhinav gupta says
if maya
were to be contradictory and for that
reason unreal
it would exist for less time than a
lightning flash
if the criterion of reality is
non-contradiction
maya would only exist less time than a
likely fraction and yet all of this is
running on contradiction
okay
now
this is another exegetical tool
for arabian avocados explaining
how why puja is effective
now don't think that this is a small
matter
because shri vidya
without abhinava gupta's
exegesis of tricker ritual
trividia would not exist
it would be
if you just read the nitisodashikaranova
it would be a very sophisticated i will
finish soon because i get tired also
well well
it would be it would be just a very
sophisticated love charm
and without the um
the yogini credit which is chocolate
block
of the terminology that's taken from the
practice
then the sri vidya would just be a very
sophisticated love child
dedicated to commercially
i mean love is important you know
you want the girl to love you or the boy
to love you
you know the certain age
um
[Music]
okay
so here is a cardinal example
now there are exegetical tools
now you understand for example in
general
there is in
i'll give you an example of a number of
exegetical tools
the concept of prasara or vikasa
consciousness
according to this traditions schools
means grammar
spander prathabigia
and abhinav prestika
is dynamic
nowhere else
amongst
is consciousness dynamic
nowhere
the
the advaita vedantic
in the room
if the
honorable sir is still there
and we're probably jumping out of his
chair
to
have to have a
a consciousness
full of action
that's just what we have to stop because
kriya gives rise to karma
now remember that the doctrine of kaaba
developed
in the plains of northern india
from around the time of the buddha
in the shamanic culture
buddhism jainism
the negrantis and all of those
and it entered into upanishads through
yagiwaki
who taught it to a student
who asked him why is there all this
suffering in this world
and he took him aside and he told him in
secret it's well known embryo
he said you know it's like a caterpillar
when it rises to the top of a blade of
grass and it molds its skin
so like this we go from body to body
because of our karma it was a secret
doctrine
and why kept secret well because you see
the people who are doing all that karma
and the youngest would get very upset
you telling us that
yagis are going to create karma
right
to keep it quiet
and iran says the olympics they didn't
accept the doctrine of karma one of the
things that kumari bhatta did was that
he
blended the doctrine of
which is what the yagi produces with the
doctrine of karma
he managed to
make it adjust that
right
now
only in
these schools do we have a dynamic
consciousness
and that's coming from the kali
traditions i won't go into all history
now that dynamic consciousness flows
there's a prasada you have this word
prasada
so from subject to object there's a
a flow
this dynamic consciousness
there is a vigilanda an unfolding
because from the subject it unfolds
through the senses into the domain of
objectivity
there is a vikasa an expansion that can
take place when limited consciousness
which is conditioned by malas and all
those things siddhanta talked about
julishavism
are removed and there's an expansion of
consciousness
and in various other occasions every
time i hear nice music there is an
expansion of consciousness so you have
the word vikasa
there is
a radiant
pulse
of consciousness so you have the word
spander and these terms you find in the
original
um
at the original scriptural level
these are all unedited texts
i first of all been to 30 40 years
going through these
thousands hundreds and thousands of
unedited texts
pages of an edited text okay
then there are some terms
which are new
that are coined by the exegetes
and one of them for example is a hambada
or a hunter
as a state of purna
means full
eye consciousness
our sense of i
i am mark is upon incomplete
if i were to think i am shiva that is
full eye consciousness okay
so this eye consciousness is made by the
interaction between the light of
consciousness and its reflective
awareness
in 1990 i wrote a paper
establishing that this terminology is
unique in indian philosophy and it
begins with paula polite
it was 10 pages that's all
but it it had a great deal to say
and the whole scholarly community
nobody ever criticized that is just
taken for granted so instead of saying
thank you they just kept quiet
foreign scholars in india are like that
we're living
there's in nazi germany
not here
it's not like that anyway
okay
now that is a a and a very important
exegetical tool
that was made by these people
who are opposed
scriptural exegetes
i described before okay
so what what i do is
i look up for all the words i can find
in scriptural sources
i see the new terms that are coming in
prior to having a gupta and then yes
and i can stop you because i'm also get
tired don't worry
but i wanted to say one thing here
that also you should notice
um and
is also very important in the history of
indian thought
in general
kashmiri uh abhinava gupta in his young
age
he wrote the commentary
on one part of bhartri hari bhakti
padilla
dealing with
the genitive and all that
so he was studying bhartiyari
from an early age
and he was very interested in
party harry and a great deal
of
concepts
that are his
that he has introduced he's drawing some
exegetical models from there
but he's also developing new exegetical
tools of his own
in linguistics
i remember in the 80s when i was a
young man
it was very fashionable at least for
foreign scholars
to talk about
linguistic analysis of mantra
what is a mantra is it language
what is the language what's the
criterion of language okay
and if so in what way is it language
this thing was being discussed
in the 80s
but nobody at that time
noticed
i'm telling you things that i've noticed
over 40 50 years
nobody at that time noticed
that abhinav gupta
had written very extensively
on
the cognitive linguistics of mantra
i call it cognitive linguistics because
party hari is a cognitive linguist
he's not just talking about how words
are structured or put together
which would be him as a grammarian he's
also talking about how we perceive
meaning
which is a perception
and it's very much intrinsic into his
analysis of language so in that way he's
a cognitive linguist
so abhinav gupta
is a cognitive linguist of
mantra
he applies a cognitive linguistic
analysis
and how does he do this
and this for him of course is very
important if we're going to talk about
ritual
and mantras
half of ritual
no
you could say
easily
so we're talking about half of what his
subject is
so he needs to have
a very good exegetical model
to talk about mantra
it doesn't mean he always
it's like the newspapers here you know
something took place
well when it goes on they don't tell you
what happened so if you're not following
from the beginning you're clueless
so
a little bit about it is like that you
have to be very careful to catch what he
says to keep the thread of his argument
in different places
he expounds
his philosophy of mantra
linguistic
mantra
in the beginning of the paratrooper
he's commenting and again it comes in
the form of a commentary
there's a commentary on the tantra
i'll go back to that i'll conclude with
that
um
he is commenting on the word dave you
archer
which is how a lot of tatars
begin not section the goddess
and there he talks about
how language
is at four levels
which nowadays we know very well
his exposition his explanation his
presentation of that is the first one we
have
in indian philosophy of these four
and it's still the best
if you're a naika you won't like it okay
because for niagara languages what you
speak or what you think
all this transcendental
language and consciousness is speaking
and that's tremendous nonsense
you know because we can prove that
but i'm saying for a lot of others
um this four land theory of speech
has become quite basic
provisionalism shame with the light you
find it
everywhere with some important
modifications
now
party hari had talked about bashanti
madhyama and vikrani
and he had done that
in order to
explain
how language works
corporeal speech the words that react
now the middle voice
is what we think
because the language thoughts are
couched in words
they may also be couched in images
but the indian
thought has never really gone into that
although it's probably
more images than words sometimes
anyway
and then there's pastianti
prashanti is
a kind of seedbed of ideas
it perceives the sense
of a sentence or of the word and in
perceiving that sense
it gives it meaning
so it extracts
from its storehouse
of archetypes
that are the meaning of words and
it
fits them on
to the word table chair whatever or the
thought of it
so
arta or
nata word and meaning
are individual
every time i say a bottle
i'm actually talking about this bottle
it's specific
but the word bottle of course applies to
all bottles
so the word barco is stored in some form
in the speech called partiality okay
in a kind of oneness with all the other
words
now there's one level of speech beyond
now this is sufficient
to explain everyday language
and this is all the party talks about
he doesn't talk about para
he doesn't need to
why
because abhinava gupta explains that
para is a hub
now aham
uh
like this it's resonating
within consciousness
it's rotating like this
or going the other way
okay
that's called shabdana
now that's
you have the term also
but he's using that for mental mental
sound
or the kind of utterance that prashanti
would be doing to infuse meaning into
words
that is to say and
to illuminating meaning
of individual words
so that process is called chapter 9
now in kashmir shaivism the word shabda
is used
for this resonance
of self-awareness of awareness
is a kind of speech
which is completely anatomic to the
buddhists
wow they sort of thought about this like
anything and you read in the privilege
of the martini those people who are
doing phds on such things
okay
now this
is mantra
the vitality of mantra
and that he tells us some other place
using another
uh exegetical model is universal spanda
samania's partner he's using the
exegetical model that's coming from the
splendor lineage
and that's universal splenda he's
telling us are the 12 kali's that is to
say
a rising persistence falling away and
the inexplicable in the domain of the
object in the domain of cognition and in
the domain of the subject
right
so like this
this is
mantra
and this is what gives mantras meaning
and it is because of that that mantras
are powerful and effective and it is
because of that that mantras have
meaning in a deeper sense i won't go on
this is a big subject now i want to
conclude saying one thing because i've
talked enough now
and
thank you for your patience
abhinav gupta called his work tantra lok
he said that he had done this under the
command of shiva who was his guru
shahbunata
and that he used
scripture
what he had learned from his guru
and vivec
is a discernment
right
that is called tantra locker
character says because it is the light
of the tantras
the light that comes from the tuttles
right
but
i would contest that
and i think the word tantra there
stands for one tantrum
is the representative of trika in the
highest sense then the whole of the
tantra loka is a commentary on the video
and you'll be glad to know
that more than half of the malindara
appears in citation
by abraham gupta or his commentator
generator
i extracted all those and actually
tantra the
video
will come as an appendix
to the tantra locker because you can't
explain why understand one without the
other okay
so
i just wanted to say how wonderful it
was
that he wasn't just
he did write commentaries like this this
is the text and underneath the
explanation
which is where we find almost everywhere
but what he did was as he quoted he
inserted his explanation
as he quoted a long passage he reduced
it to one or two lions
when he
caught from one tantra he would quote
from another to justify it and then add
his own
little bit
so that it forms a stream of continuity
so you couldn't know where he's speaking
and where the tantra is speaking
right
unless you know that oh he is applying
these exegetical tools it must be hidden
now what that does is it creates a text
which is not just a compendium
in fact we researched for 40 years
to recover
all the texts that he refers to
we say we know are prior to him
and the ones that we have found that
were not in print almost all in nepal
i spent decades editing them
tens and thousands of pages
i spent editing them
the dikshatra four shotguns of
the tantrasad
etc but not so many
right
and very very carefully analyzing
all the the references
to try and understand the character of
the tattoos that he's quoting
he
prefers
trick-or-treaters that are very calmer
extreme left hand he considers ritual
in which siddhas and yoginis perform
rights together
to be the highest kind of ritual
for which very few are hours
all that takes place in very rare
moments in one's life
let's put it that way
okay
he considered this to be supreme
so his form of trika is kaola
there's no separate cowalism
that is tricker
and the cowardism of his trika is taken
mostly from kramer sources that worship
khani so she's the supreme goddess
not sheila
and finally the
okay
so
his
tantra loca
is written in such a way
adopting all these essences
from all the shaiva agama
combined with this personal insight
that it is scripture
those who read this tantra locker
they
can achieve liberation
i mean that's quite a thing to say you
know
imagine mark dzkovsky wrote a book and
on the cover says if you read this and
understand it you get liberation
they i don't know how many people take
me straight to court i'd have crowds
outside my house so we paid
is very convincing
i don't say how close i got to
liberation i was like
that's my whatever come to me
okay
so
uh exegesis
revelation and its exegesis
these two together
form a powerful
combination
that can give us liberation in this life
and at the same time it can explain to
us
not only tell us what the tantras are
saying
but what they
mean and this gives us guyana
and through ghana we get porkchop
and if you don't want that you get a lot
of other benefits also
maybe in a young age a good job in
university with a massive salary in
harvard
i'm just joking
so
thank you very much and for your
patience
[Applause]
thank you dr mark for your
beautiful lecture
so much enlightening to all of us
but
we are only halfway through i must
remind
and we shall have a tree wake right now
after that the second part of his
lecture would continue
and this is this
if you want or maybe if you don't want
to continue with the lecture
so
no it's okay if you don't want to
continue with the lecture then we'll
have the discussion after the tea break
because discussion also is very
important there must be you know many
questions coming up
very important so maybe we'll have just
the discussion in the second part and
this is again so after the discussion is
over don't forget to take the prasad and
then after that you can go
so let's proceed for tea break okay
i would request the online participants
to kindly join us in 15 minutes it's
around 1 o'clock right now and we'll be
again starting at 1 15. thank you
you